How many of you have
never seen me be fixed dollars?
So that's philosophy number one,
wait for the government to change the minimum wage.
You say, well, that might take too long.
Is there another philosophy?
And the answer is yes.
Okay, here's the second philosophy.
Wait for the company to pay you $6 an hour.
Right, you get a review, how often?
Every six months, let's say.
You missed it, you waited a year,
maybe you didn't make it then.
You say, well, no telling how long.
If you've got a thousand people with you,
maybe you could force the company
to change it from five to six.
If there were enough of you
that said, we will not work,
we demand $6 or we will not work.
By yourself, not a good philosophy.
Together with others, it could work.
Right, here's what we call this, the philosophy of demand.
I demand more money.
Alone, too risky.
Together, maybe you could get some progress.
So now we've covered three philosophies.
Number one, wait for the government.
Number two, wait for the company.
Number three, the philosophy of demand,
which is a bit risky.
Here's the problem with the philosophy of demand.
You can't get rich.
If people only understood, starting at the bottom,
starting at the lower end of the economic scale,
that you cannot get rich by demand.
Now someone says, well, in America,
how could you become wealthy?
And the answer is to develop a new philosophy.
And let me give you that.
It might be the best
I've got for the whole day.
It's called the philosophy of performance.
The philosophy of performance.
I will perform so well,
it would be embarrassing,
for the company not to pay me $6.
Then I would perform so well,
it would be embarrassing for the company
not to pay me $8 an
hour, $10 an hour, $20 an hour.
So now we've got several philosophies going.
And if you want to change your economic future,
it starts with your personal philosophy.
Now here's what's interesting in America.
I'm sure all of us can do this.
I can think of someone who
makes $5 an hour getting started.
Can anybody in the audience think of someone
who makes $50 an hour?
Do you happen to know
anyone that makes $50 an hour?
Anybody know somebody that makes about that much money?
So jot this down now,
because you've got to teach it to the children,
because they're not teaching this in the ordinary schools.
It's possible in America to multiply your income by 10.
If you take nothing else home economically
to pass onto your children or to someone else,
just take that phrase home.
Jim Rohn taught us,
it's possible in America to multiply your income by 10.
It's possible.
If kids knew it was possible,
do you think they would
ask, how can you do that?
If they knew it was possible,
wouldn't the next question would
be, how could I do it?
If it's possible, how can I do it?
Now you'd just teach them how to do it.
How could I do it?
How to multiply your income by 10.
Now, jot this down.
A good economic question.
Once you've multiplied your income by 10,
is it possible to multiply it by 10 again?
Not only to multiply it by 10,
but to multiply your income by 10 again.
Again.
Do you know anybody that makes $500 an hour?
Can you think of someone?
Makes $500 an hour?
Right.
My Beverly Hills lawyer makes more than $500 an hour.
So jot this down.
It's not only possible in America
to multiply your income by 10,
it's possible to multiply it by 10 again.
Do you think kids would
be excited to hear this philosophy?
I'm sure they would.
How can you multiply your income by 10
and then multiply it by 10 again?
Now, if you multiplied it by 10
and then multiplied it again by 10,
would it be possible,
would it be possible
to multiply it by 10 again?
Can you think of anybody that makes $5,000 an hour?
What do you think I get paid?
I mean, this is such exciting stuff.
I'm a kid.
I'm a kid from the farms of Idaho.
I was 25 years old before I learned
that you could multiply your income by 10
and then multiply it by 10 again
and then multiply it by 10 again.
Again.
This is mind-boggling stuff.
$5,000 an hour.
Now, would it be possible,
would it be possible
to multiply it by 10 again?
Again.
Just to make sure the math is correct,
is $5,000 an hour an hour?
$5,000 an hour.
Now, here's a good expression to use,
especially for this group.
You're all tuned in,
especially the last couple of days.
The best expression is,
of course.
Could you multiply your income by 10?
Of course.
Could you do it again?
Could you do it one more time?
Of course.
50 times an hour.
$50,000 an hour.
You know, I've lectured with General Schwarzkopf
and Colin Powell.
I had lunch once with
Colin Powell a few years ago.
Schwarzkopf gets about $65,000 for a one-hour speech.
So how could you finally get to $50,000 an hour?
Answer, become a general in the Army.
Yes.
And lead the troops in the Gulf War.
But what I'm trying to say is the possibilities here,
let's just say, are just unlimited.
You can multiply your income by 10,
then you can multiply it by 10 again,
and you can multiply it by 10 again.
Now, we're only talking economic values.
There's all kinds of other values
in terms of personal development, but this is it.
Now, to climb this ladder, here's the possibilities.
$63 million last year, one person earned.
The possibilities, we would have to say, in our country,
is what we call unlimited.
Now, to climb this ladder as
high as you wish to climb it.
Jot this phrase down now,
because I don't think I'll talk about anything more valuable
than what I'm about to share with you.
Here it is.
To climb this ladder economically as high as you wish,
you climb it.
Here's all you have to do.
Learn to work harder on yourself
than you do on your job.
Once I understood that philosophy,
it totally changed my life.
I made my first fortune by
age 32, starting at age 25.
And I've made...
I've lost a few fortunes since then.
That one simple philosophy,
that it's possible to multiply your income by 10,
and then by 10, and then by 10, by 10.
And here's the simple way to do it.
Work harder on yourself than you do on your job.
Here's how it was put to me.
If you work hard on your
job, you can make a living,
which is fantastic.
If you work hard on
yourself, you can make a fortune.
Which is super fantastic.
At age 25, I went to work on myself.
The difference in my economic future was so startling,
even in the early years, that I
never went back to the old ways.
I never went back to the old philosophy.
I never went back to the old disciplines.
I accepted the new ones,
and it changed my life forever.
Unbelievable.
Here it is in fact.
I'm going to use philosophical terms.
Just jot this phrase down.
This is a good one.
Success is something you attract
by becoming an attractive person.
Success is not something you pursue.
Success is something you attract
by the person you become,
by becoming an attractive person.
Now, what could you think of
that would start to make you
more attractive to the marketplace?
This is such simple ABC stuff.
Okay?
Let me give it to you.
Let me start with this.
Jim Rohn's view of the 21st century.
We've begun a new century, 21.
We've begun a new millennium, number seven.
Some scholars hold great significance
to this seventh millennium.
And I think it's probably true.
It's going to be the most extraordinary time
in the history of the human race, I think.
And these opening years now of the new millennium
and the new century,
how could you take advantage
of this extraordinary time in human history
and make for yourself an extraordinary life?
Because it's all possible.
So jot this little quote down now.
It's one of the best I've
come up with, I think, lately.
And I'll just quote it slowly
so you can jot it down and take it home.
Here it is.
From testimonials
and from personal experience,
we have enough information
to conclude
that it's possible
to design
and build
and live
an extraordinary life.
From testimonials and from personal experience,
we have enough information to conclude
that it's possible to design and build and live
an extraordinary life.
I'd like to have you think about that,
not just here,
but even after you've gone back home.
Think about it at least often enough
to say,
I think that's true.
From testimonials
and from personal experience,
we have enough information to conclude
that it's possible to design and build
and live an extraordinary life.
From testimonials and from personal experience,
we have enough information to conclude
that it's possible
to design and build and live
an extraordinary life.
Now if you believe that and accept it,
you just simply use that as a foundation,
as the fundamentals.
So now jot this down.
Jim Rohn's view of the 21st century.
Number one,
unprecedented opportunity.
Unprecedented opportunity.
These are probably going to be
the most extraordinary times
in the history of the human race,
6,000 years of recorded history.
We got through the last millennium.
We especially got through the last century,
a bloody century,
the 20th century.
Hopefully those major wars of devastation
and destruction are behind us.
World War II claimed 50 million lives.
19 million of them were Russian.
The devastation of the 20th century
was unparalleled and unprecedented.
The savagery was unbelievable.
The Holocaust was insanity
of the most unbelievable kind.
Hopefully that is in the century past.
And that we have a new chance
in a new century
to build a new world
and a new country
and a new future.
With all of the challenges.
With Saddam Hussein,
with the terrorists
and all the rest.
Once the walls came down
about 12, 13 years ago,
and I was just in Berlin
the other day lecturing
and had a chance to go to the Brandenburg Gate,
Checkpoint Charlie,
see part of the old Berlin Wall.
Once those walls came down 13 years ago,
the world now has forever changed.
Because here's how the history
of the human race reads.
Opportunity mixed with difficulty.
Sometimes more difficulty than opportunity.
The history of the human race reads
tyranny and liberty.
Sometimes more tyranny than liberty.
But now the world has totally changed.
Since communism is on the run,
the dead are on the run.
The dictators, most of them,
are all gone.
When I used to lecture years ago
in South America,
every country had a dictator.
Now they're all gone.
Castro and a few are left,
but that's it.
And they will soon all be gone.
Within a short little period
of the rest of our lifetime,
all the dictators will be gone.
A new wave of economic uniqueness,
capitalism, free enterprise,
liberty, freedom, democracy
is absolutely sweeping the world.
So for a long dark time,
there was more tyranny than liberty.
Here's what is unique about this new century 21.
More liberty than tyranny.
More freedom than oppression.
This is an unprecedented time.
Unbelievable opportunity.
We have the technology to accomplish
the most incredible things.
We pick up a telephone now
and talk to somebody
on the other side of the world
with ease.
It's incredible.
We fly.
We've got transportation.
I get on an airplane.
Thirteen hours later,
I'm in Hong Kong.
Five meals, three movies,
and you're there.
I mean, it's unbelievable.
I leave at 7.30 this evening
to fly all night to Orlando
to speak to another group
tomorrow in Orlando.
It's amazing.
With the jets,
you can cover the world.
I fly the Concorde
three hours long.
to London, New York.
If you fly the Concorde,
you can see two sunsets
in one day.
If you're in London,
when the sun goes down,
you fly the Concorde
to New York,
you watch the sun go down
for the second time.
I told the group
at our little breakfast meeting
this morning,
if you fly the Concorde
due west,
the sun comes up in the west.
If you haven't tried that,
you must try it.
On the Concorde,
you meet unique people.
I met Henry Kissinger
on the Concorde.
He said,
I'm going to fly
the Concorde
to New York.
I'm going to fly
the Concorde
to New York.
I met Henry Kissinger
on the Concorde.
Henry said,
I had breakfast in Paris.
I'm having lunch
here in London.
I'm having dinner
tonight in New York.
If you fly the Concorde.
Before his accident,
I met Christopher Reeves
a couple of times
on the Concorde.
I said to my business partner,
we're going to be okay.
Superman's on this plane.
This is unprecedented opportunity
now, the 21st century
and the beginning
of the seventh millennium.
These are extraordinary times.
Now here's number two.
However, keen competition,
world competition.
We're dealing now with Iraq.
A big part of it is competition.
Hopefully the nations of the world
will settle a big share
of their differences
so we can develop unique economic,
social, personal prosperity
for the future
with limited conflicts.
No more horrors.
No more holocausts.
Hopefully.
But with the human race,
you always have to keep
your fingers crossed.
Who knows?
But I think it's going to be
a time of unprecedented opportunity,
but unique competition.
Now to take advantage
of the 21st century
and this opening
of the new millennium,
how could you use
the opportunity?
Mind.
Now that you've arrived,
told me your story,
I'm beginning to see the light.
Words.
The old prophet said this,
words are like a lamp for your feet
so you can see where to walk.
And words are like a light
for your pathway
so you can see where to go.
With words, you can show somebody
where to step and where to go.
Wow.
I said a little prayer
before I left my hotel room
this morning
and asked God to give me
a little stronger gift of words today
so that my words might have meaning.
Maybe I've caught you
at just the right time.
Maybe this is the moment for you.
And if I can say something
uniquely enough,
using the English language
best as I can.
Words are sometimes clumsy
when you try to express
what's going on in your head,
let alone your heart.
But if I can do as good a job
as I possibly can
in the session we've got this morning
and then again this afternoon,
by the time I'm finished,
maybe my words will help turn on
another light for you.
And you'll be able to see
the possibilities
better than you've ever seen it before.
You'll be able to see yourself
more successful
than you've ever envisioned it before.
If I can wisely say good words.
Now I've put communication in three parts
because all three of these parts
now help me make more fortunes.
Here's the first one.
It's called training.
Training is simply showing somebody
how to do the business,
how to do the job.
If you get good at that,
the pay is incredible.
Whether it's your own enterprise
or whether you work for someone else.
Training pays big money.
Here's the next one.
Teaching.
And I've divided the two
just to make the point.
Teaching is more teaching life skills.
Life skills.
Teach somebody how to set goals.
Gary mentioned, right,
making the list and checking them off.
Today he gets to check one off.
Jim Rohn arrives in San Jose, Santa Clara.
I'm so excited about that.
Teaching leadership.
Teaching management.
Teaching how to become powerful,
gifted, influential.
Teaching father skills, mother skills.
I've now the last 15 years learned grandfather skills.
I set a goal when I became a grandfather
to be one of the best grandfathers
any grandchild ever had in the whole wide world.
I practice it.
I think about it.
How to use my new found life as a grandfather
and learn every skill I need.
And learn every skill possible
to dazzle my grandchildren.
I'm one of the best.
So teach people how to be good fathers,
good grandfathers, good mothers,
good leaders in the community.
Teach a minister how to teach.
Teach a minister how to use the gift of language
to persuade.
Okay.
So communication is part of its training,
part of its teaching.
Here's the best part.
No, here's number three in the gift of language.
And that's learning how to inspire.
Inspire simply means a few simple things.
Here's number one.
Help people to see themselves better than they are.
Yes, sometimes we have to help people
see themselves as they are.
If they've made mistakes,
maybe that needs to be pointed out.
If a child has messed up,
sometimes you've got to say,
you've messed up.
But don't leave them in the mess.
Now transport them into the future
with the gift of your language.
And inspire them with the person they can become
by using the mistakes of the past
to develop new disciplines for the future.
A teacher I met when I was 25 years old
had this unusual gift.
He said,
Mr. Rohn, if you keep learning as you're learning now,
one of these days you'll walk
into a room full of people
and you'll hear someone say,
there's the man.
That's the man.
That's the famous man.
I thought, well, that could never happen for me.
Sure enough, it did.
He said, it will happen.
And I think when I walked in here this morning,
I heard someone say,
that's him.
That's the man.
That's the famous man.
It's accurate.
That's the best man.
It's a man.
It just helps me realize
for real,
he said,
of language that can do that. Help them to
have faith for themselves and faith for the future.
The sacred writing says this, faith comes
by hearing words, good words. Somebody who well
chooses their words and delivers them with
uniqueness can inspire faith for somebody to
believe the most impossible things can be
possible. And those, that excitement of possibilities
comes from hearing or reading unique words.
One of the best phrases I could give you for
the day, here it is, don't be lazy in language.
Don't be lazy in language because the
gift of language can create a career.
It can help somebody see the way into the future.
It can help somebody change from who they are to
who they would like to be. It will help you
to see the gift of your own intellect. There's an
innate relationship between you and somebody who
loves you. And there's an innate relationship
between you and somebody who loves you. And there's
an innate relationship between you and somebody who's not.
vocabulary in all of us that helps us to
see, helps us to translate what's going on in the
world, what's happening, so that we can make good
decisions instead of poor ones. We can make less
mistakes this year than we made last year. One of
the major things to pray for is to be gifted
in language, because it can have such a dynamic
effect on your children. It can have such a dynamic
effect on your business. It can have such a
dynamic effect on your customers. It can have such a
dynamic effect on your business partners. That not
to continually get better and better at the gift
of language would be a great mistake. Let it
open doors. Nothing else will open the gift of your
language. Let it help people to see possibilities that
they cannot see now. And you join in in those
possibilities and make another fortune and another fortune, all
the way up the ladder as far as you
wish to go.
I don't know if you've ever heard of the phrase,
I don't know how high you need to go.
What were the instructions given to the first
couple after the garden experience, Adam and Eve,
according to the storyteller? We've got some
Bible scholars here right now. Instructions given to
Adam and Eve after the garden experience. Here
they are. Number one, multiply. It's a lonely
place with just two people. Multiply. But here's one
now that is so extraordinary, and I'm going to
cover a little bit more of it during our
ongoing session here today. Here was the second one. Be
fruitful. Be fruitful, kind of an interesting
phrase. When I lecture in other countries,
sometimes it's difficult to find the right
translation for be fruitful. Here's what I
think fruitful means.
Be productive. The example might be a tree, a fruit tree.
Plant a fruit tree. Now, why do that? It's very simple.
Teach it to your children. Number one, to survive.
The first instinct is to survive. So be productive
enough to survive. Be productive enough for your own survival.
But is that the end of it? The answer is no,
that's only the beginning of it.
To produce enough for yourself is only the beginning. What's
the rest? Here's number two. Get married. Now you've got to
think of ways to produce more than you need for yourself. And
guess what that does? It elevates you to a higher life. If you
want to live this higher life of a companion, a
wife, getting married, see that now changes the dynamics of your
future. It's called stepping up to a better life. And to
step up to a better life, here's what you simply do
economically. You learn to provide and figure out a way
to provide more than you need for yourself. You think of
ways to provide enough for yourself and for someone else.
Why think of someone else? Why not just think of
yourself? Because that's a very limited way to live. Just thinking
of your own survival. If you want to live a more
flourishing life, then you need to think of how to provide more
than you need for yourself. You need to think of how to
unique life you must think now of someone
else so now the man says I must
produce enough for myself and for my
wife is that the end of the life
experience no now have children take a risk
having a child is like a throw of
the genetic dice who knows what's coming
see what happens but now a man
who now wants the experience of having children
must now think of ways to produce
enough for himself and for his family some
says why do that why not just
take care of yourself because that's such a
beginning way to live
survivalism is a way to live
okay but it's not the good life now take it
a step further jot this one down a
man now figures out because he's learned it
now he's experienced and he understands what
life is all about now he figures
out how to produce more than he needs
for himself and for his family just got
the word down more keep thinking more how
could I produce more than I need for
myself and for my family
Someone says, why do that?
And the answer is to live a higher life,
because now you can be generous.
Now you can support worthy projects.
Is that it?
No.
Here's the next one.
To produce much more than you need for yourself
and for your family.
Someone says, why do that?
And the answer is to live this higher life.
What if you earned $10 million one year
and you and your family only needed 3 million?
That would probably take care
of the average family, 3 million.
Some families are more expensive than others,
but let's say 3 million would pretty well take care
of most families.
But you made 10 million,
and you and your family only needed 3 million.
Now you've got that.
You've got $7 million to give.
Wouldn't you like to live that kind of life?
Whew.
Someone says, why do that?
And the answer is, the possibilities of economics
are so available that if you wish to,
you can not only earn enough
for yourself and for your family,
you can earn more than you
need for yourself and for your family.
And if you wish to, you can
earn more than you need for yourself
and for your family, and if you wish to, you can
earn more than you need for yourself and for your family.
really wanted to you could earn much
more than you need for yourself and for
your family
is that it let's take it one
step further just got this phrase down figure
out a way to earn far more than
you need for yourself and for your family
Gary talked about Mark Hughes I met Mark when
he was 19 I still do a lot of work
for Herbalife around the world he
started this little company when he was
22 23 called Herbalife and he
died just a couple of years ago
Mark Hughes age 44 guess what he
left number one a company worth 680 million
dollars according to the new investors here's
what he left his son 350 million
you
I do some estimated wealth he created
for those who worked for him during the
20 years he was alive about three and
a half billion imagine having the zest and
having the wish and having the desire
to create billions in wealth not just for
yourself but for others 350 million
nice little nest egg for your son
somebody says why do that
can you think of the best answer ever
jump this phrase down why not right what
else are you gonna do just hang in there
until the bitter end No why not see how
far up this economic ladder you can possibly
go to see if you can't live an
extraordinary life
just an ordinary life, that's okay. Survival,
that's okay. You and your family, that's okay.
But if you could think larger than that, so that
you really go to work on seeing who you could
become in terms of influence, in terms
of productivity, in terms of living the little
phrase I give you called an extraordinary life.
Ordinary would be okay. Extraordinary would be the best.
Isn't this good stuff? Couldn't wait to
get here and tell you about it.
I could hardly wait to hear
what I've got to say today.
Okay, so number one, to
take advantage of the 21st century,
let me make sure I'm on track here.
To take advantage of the 21st century,
learn multiple skills. Let me give you one more now.
It would be useful to know more than one language.
When I travel the world, I have to
have translators. The only way I can speak to
someone in Japan or speak to someone in South
Africa or speak to someone in Israel or speak
to someone in Europe most of the time,
I have to have someone translate for me.
Somebody has to know more than one language to
translate for me. And their gift of knowing more
than one language makes them uniquely valuable. So
that would be another wise idea. Learn more than
one language and number two, learn more than
one skill. Number two, learn more than one language.
When I was growing up, my father spoke German.
He was German, but he never taught me German.
I could have learned it. My mother was English,
but she spoke French, but she never taught me
the French. When I was growing up, they said, you know, leave
the old world languages behind. This is America now. English, English, English.
This is America now. English, English, English.
Now we know much better. My parents, I could
have learned three languages as easy as one growing up.
So, if you think the time has passed
for you to learn that second and third language,
make this note now, it's one of the best for
the day. Give it as a gift to your children.
Encourage them to learn the second, third
language, as many as they can learn.
I asked the teacher one time, how many
languages can a child learn? And she said,
said, as many as you will teach them.
They don't lack curiosity. They don't lack capacity. They
only lack a teacher. Don't let your child develop
10% of what they're capable of. Don't let them
develop 15% of what they're capable of. Give
them the opportunity to learn as much percentage as
possible of what they're capable of,
and for yourself. So, multiple skills, multiple
自己在捲曲對手的聲音
Now what's the rest?
Taking advantage of the 21st century.
Jot these notes down.
Have you got this?
Don't wanna erase it if you haven't got it.
I've got five key things to talk about
during my presentation for the day, five.
Five good basic ideas.
These are called basics, fundamentals.
And it's interesting that I only have five.
How many fundamentals are there to anything?
Here's a good phrase, just a few,
meaning anybody can learn them.
There's just a few fundamentals to being healthy.
If someone says, I'm gonna teach you
the 50 fundamentals to good health,
you say, well, that doesn't make sense.
There's not
50 fundamentals to have good health.
There's just a few, six, seven, eight, that's about it.
If you wanna learn to play basketball,
you gotta learn the fundamentals.
How many fundamentals are there to the game of basketball?
Just a few, five, six, if you become extremely gifted,
maybe seven, eight, that's it, that's it.
Now here's what's interesting also about fundamentals.
There's no new ones.
I mean, this stuff's been around for a long time.
So beware of someone who says we got new truths.
Say, no, truth is old.
It can be, more of it can be discovered,
but there's no new truth.
If someone says, I'm manufacturing antiques,
wouldn't you be a little suspicious?
Say, no.
I'm not.
So skills and fundamentals are like antiques.
They've been around forever.
The law of averages I
teach in one of my seminars,
the law of averages,
here's what it says.
If you do something often enough,
you'll soon have a ratio of results.
Talk to 10 more, get another one.
Talk to 10 more, get two instead of one.
Why is that?
You're getting better.
The law of averages works for anyone.
One we've learned for a long time.
Here it is.
It doesn't ever change.
Whether it's a church or a business,
20% of the people do 80%.
80% do 20%.
So here's what I learned in time management.
You can spend 80% of your time with the 20%,
not the 80%.
You spend 20% of your time with the 80%,
80% of your time with the 20%.
You just have to learn.
And these fundamentals now have been around
for a long, long time.
The 80-20 rule.
We bring products, tapes, books, videos, right?
Things to buy for your ongoing education.
We bring books and tapes and CDs.
We bring all that stuff for how many people?
You say, well, you'd bring
enough for 100% of the people.
No.
You bring all the stuff for the 20%.
Not the 80%.
Isn't that fascinating?
It's fascinating.
People's different reaction to the same presentation.
Someone walks out of my seminar and says,
wow,
I'm going to go change my life.
Someone else walks out and says,
I've heard all this stuff before.
Same seminar.
It said the first day the Christian church was started,
first day, the speaker, Peter, got up,
gave this classic presentation to a multitude,
vast number of people.
And what was interesting was when he finished
the reaction to his presentation,
it said some of the, I think,
the most important things about the presentation,
I think there were like, there were thousands.
It said some of them laughed at him.
And I thought, why would they laugh?
He seemed sincere to me.
And it said some of them mocked him.
And I thought, why would they do that?
Then I found out they're the mockers.
That's what they're supposed to do.
And the laughers are supposed to laugh.
It said some that heard this magnificent presentation
didn't know what was going on.
And they're easy to spot.
They're usually saying what's going on, right?
I mean, they don't know what's happening.
But then it says this.
Some,
that heard, believed.
And the number that believed was about 3,000.
Didn't give us the total,
but out of the total, 3,000 said,
hey, this is good enough to follow.
So that's life.
Once you learn the percentages, right?
It's called the law of averages.
It's one of the best studies.
It's in some of my CDs and presentations.
But now,
let's talk about the fundamentals of life,
the fundamentals of success.
There's just a few.
They're basic.
It's like ABCs, which I deal with primarily, ABCs.
So let's go through them.
Here's number one.
We've talked a little bit about it.
By way of introductory, it's called,
one, your personal philosophy.
And it's a little bit more than that.
It's a little bit more than that.
Philosophy is a big subject.
Political philosophy.
Here's what the communists taught,
because I have to deal with
it when I go to Russia.
The communists taught,
capital belongs to the state, not the people.
We've taught all these years what?
Capital belongs to the people, not the state.
Wow, what a difference in economic philosophy.
The communists said, people are
too dumb and stupid and greedy
to know what to do with capital.
So you've got to take capital away
from all the dumb, stupid, greedy people
and give all the capital to the all-wise, all-knowing state.
And let the state run everything,
and let the dumb, stupid people
show up for their work assignment.
That was the philosophy of communism.
They devastated every country
they touched with that philosophy.
I was just in East Germany.
Guess what it's taking just to clean
up East Germany after the communists left?
A trillion dollars.
They've spent $500 billion already,
and they've got another $500 billion to go
just to clean up one
country devastated by such a philosophy.
Capital belongs to the state, not the people.
Wow.
The consequences of philosophy are,
unbelievably, either on the good
side or on the bad side.
Now, personal philosophy.
You know, there's religious
philosophy and spiritual philosophy,
and there's economic philosophy and social philosophy.
Okay?
Economic, political, all kinds of philosophies.
Right?
Where did we come from and where are we going?
What is the meaning of life?
Philosophy is a big tent with many different divisions.
But the one I want to talk primarily about today,
and then expand from that,
is your personal philosophy.
So jot this down.
One of the best notes for the day.
Each person's personal philosophy
is the greatest determining factor
in how your life works out.
Each person's personal philosophy
is the greatest determining factor
in how your life works out.
Your economic life, your personal life,
your social life, your spiritual life.
All starts with the conclusions you've made
in your personal philosophy.
We gave the example earlier on economics.
There's three or four different philosophies to choose from
in your economic future.
Now, make this note.
Personal philosophy is like a guidance system.
A guidance system.
And it has to start early.
When a child goes to school,
they've got to have a pretty good guidance system working.
And this guidance system does just two things primarily.
Here's number one.
This guidance system helps you
to see the dangers over here.
And try to minimize those,
or eliminate some of those,
some of those.
That's one of the first orders of human existence,
is to learn early where the dangers are
so they don't swallow you up,
don't devastate you economically, socially, personally,
or lose your life.
Kids have to get this guidance system working early
to spot the signals of the dangers
that could wreck their chances to live a good life.
Now, this guidance system,
also helps you to see over here the opportunities
so that you could maximize those.
So if you learn to minimize the dangers,
maximize the opportunities
within this working environment now,
we call this working things
out to live a good life.
But you can't possibly live much of a good life
if you don't keep learning
where the dangers are,
so you can avoid those,
and learn where the opportunities are
so that you can maximize those.
That's about as simple as I can put
working on your personal philosophy.
Now, why is it this way?
Why is life both danger and opportunity?
Here's the best advice I can give you.
The storyteller probably gives us,
you know, more to think about than in detail.
But here's what it seems like.
And that's one of the best phrases to use
if you're going to make your studies
and try to come to some good conclusions.
It seems like,
it seems like,
God wished to create
for the humans he made,
a great adventure.
Seems like.
According to the storyteller,
it seems like God wished to create
a great adventure for the humans he created.
That's the best explanation I've got.
Seems like.
And it seems like God's always wanted
some kind of adventure.
It said when he was alone in heaven,
according to the storyteller,
he created all these angels.
That must have been fun.
He created all these angels.
Doesn't say how long it took.
Doesn't say how many.
But evidently,
he sought adventure.
Part of the adventure, I guess,
in those early times before the creation,
was in heaven with the angels he created.
Now then, he also creates an angel
that's the best and the brightest of the angels
called Lucifer.
And so begins, according to the storyteller,
one of the great adventures of all time.
And along the way,
the idea occurred to Lucifer
that he could take over God's place,
become God in his place.
And he persuaded, according to the storyteller,
he persuaded a third of the angels
to go with him on this insurrection.
So begins an unbelievable adventure.
Seems like that's what God wishes.
Some great adventure.
Not just sit up there
and float around on a cloud.
Create some angels, create Lucifer.
Lucifer persuades a third of the angels
to go with him in insurrection.
Now they lose out.
And uniquely enough, according to the storyteller,
God doesn't kill them all.
That would end the adventure.
But rather cast them out of heaven
down into the sea.
And so, in the end,
God gives them a chance to go to heaven.
But rather cast them out of heaven down to earth.
And so now continues this unique story of Lucifer
and his, the third of
the angels now cast to earth,
creates another adventure.
Interesting.
The Bible is such a fascinating book,
giving us seemingly,
you know, what God delights in
and seems like God delights
in creating this unique adventure.
One of the ancient stories says
God and Satan were talking things over one day.
I thought, well, that doesn't seem possible.
But the storyteller says they're looking down on the earth
and they're talking things over.
I thought, wow, that's remarkable.
God and Satan getting together
and talking things over.
Now the storyteller doesn't give us many details.
So we've got to use our imagination.
And on this particular occasion,
God got to bragging on one of his favorite creation.
His favorite person.
It's called Job.
He said, Job and I
have got this great friendship going.
Job and I, we walk together.
Job and I plan the future together.
Job, Job, Job.
Finally, Satan headed up to here with
And he said, yeah, God,
Job, you've got a wall built around him.
I can't get to him.
God said, well, what would you expect?
He's my favorite person.
Of course, I've got a wall built around him.
Now they're having this conversation.
It's fascinating.
Storyteller says, Satan gets this bright idea.
He said, hey, God, let's try this.
God said what?
If you'll take the wall of protection down
from around your favorite friend, Job,
he said, I promise you
within a short period of time,
your favorite friend will curse you to your face.
God said, no, he'd never do it.
Not in 100 years, no matter what.
Satan said, well, how are we going to know?
Would you like to make a wager?
It doesn't give us the details of the wager.
But the storyteller says God picked up the bet.
And said, okay, let's try it.
I'll take the wall down
from around my special friend, Job.
You do your best.
I promise you no matter what
you do, he'll never curse me.
Satan said, the bet is on.
According to the terms of the wager,
God did take the wall down
from around his special friend, Job.
And Satan then does one of his all-time famous numbers.
According to the storyteller,
first, Satan took his wealth.
Stripped him of his wealth.
Satan said, that'll do it.
Where's your friend, God?
He didn't curse God.
Satan said, well.
Number two, took his health.
Below number two.
Surely now he'll curse his friend, God.
No.
Below number three and the worst.
Took his family.
His health, his wealth, and his family.
Gone.
Satan said to God, here's where he does it.
And sure enough, Job's wife comes along and says,
Job, looks like your friend, God, has long forsaken you.
You might as well curse him and die.
And Satan said, here's where he does it.
And God says, well, he hasn't talked yet.
And while they both listen, Job says,
never would I curse my
friend, God, no matter what happens.
God said, I knew it.
I knew it.
And picked up the bet.
Whatever it was, doesn't tell it.
Isn't that a fascinating story?
Now, I say all of that to illustrate this.
It seems like God delights in great adventure.
And the only way to have
great adventure is to have God's love.
And the only way to
have great adventure, it seems like,
is to have both danger and opportunity,
and us with the possibility of figuring it out.
Jot this down.
Now, it's a nice little list.
...from other people is to just pick up the signals.
Part of it is by sight.
Here's a good watchword for the 21st century.
Pay attention.
No use falling into the
same trap somebody else fell into.
No use living a mediocre
life like somebody else has chosen.
Take a look and say, is
that what you really would like?
Say, no.
Here's somebody that never read
the books, never made the changes.
There was a class and they didn't take
it, a skill and they never learned it,
a discipline and they never tried it.
And they blame the government
and blame taxes and blame society.
And they blame circumstances and all the rest.
They don't know.
And the key is, watch carefully.
Don't you fall into that same trap.
That's how we learn from what we see.
Here's next.
If we learn from what we see,
we put some of this on video
so you can see it again and again and again.
Next, you learn from what you hear.
We put it on CDs so you
can hear it and hear it, hear it.
We don't ask you to come to just one seminar.
We ask you to come and listen again, listen again.
Here's what the early Christians were taught.
Don't neglect the assembly.
When we call an assembly,
do your best to be there.
Because you never know which of these
assemblies is going to change your life forever.
You'll never be the same again.
And you can't pick the one
that's going to totally change your life.
You just have to do like
all of you I know do.
Consistently go, consistently go,
consistently go, consistently take notes,
consistently go to seminars, lectures, and all of the rest,
because some of them will be life-changing.
Maybe this one will be for some of you.
The time is right.
The words are right.
The ideas are right.
The moment is here.
We don't know.
We just come as many times as we can.
Be affected by as much language as we can.
And see what that will do
for our sight and our ambition,
our willingness to develop skills.
Be a leader, influential.
Here's the next one.
Be a selective listener.
Don't just load up on
stuff that isn't going to count.
We all need a little humor.
But not that much.
Life is a pretty sober place.
It's life or death.
It's success or failure.
It's flourishing or mediocrity.
It's serious matter.
So, make sure that what you
listen to gives you the full range,
a good diet of things to listen to.
The positive, yes, but the negative also.
We need to hear it from both sides.
Okay?
Years ago, I saw an advertisement once on Roseanne.
Turn into Roseanne, white chicks talking trash.
I thought, oh, America needs more of that.
Now, you don't need much
of that, white chicks talking trash.
Here's a good note.
This is a good one.
My teacher taught me when I was 25,
stand guard at the door of your mind.
Stand guard at the door of your mind.
And you decide what to listen
to, what not to listen to.
How much time to give to what.
Now, the third one is important,
and when we come back this afternoon, we'll continue it.
But here's number three.
Read all the books.
Now, there's millions of books, so
you can't read all the books.
But here's what I mean by reading all the books.
Read all the books you need to read to make your fortune
become powerful, influential, healthy, prosperous, aware, bright, helpful, partnership, father, mother, grandparent.
Read all the books you
need for your life to flourish
and become the best it can possibly
be during the course of your lifetime.
Read all of those books.
Don't be short on that list.
My library certainly won't do it.
I've only written four or five books.
I'm working now on my fifth.
I think it's my fifth book.
It's going to be for teenagers and college kids.
And I think the title is going to be,
Of course, kids should pay taxes.
Of course.
It's going to be an interesting book on capitalism.
Because I teach capitalism now
in Russia in very simple form.
I might give you a couple
notes on that when we return.
I teach kids how to have two
bicycles, one to ride and one to rent.
It doesn't take long to get
into business and make a profit.
Here's what changed my life and
helped me make my first fortune.
Jot this down.
The philosophy that helped me make my first fortune.
Profits are better than wages.
Once I understood that,
it was hard to sleep nights the first year.
Profits are better than wages.
Wages make you a living, which is fine.
Profits make you a fortune, which is super fine.
And when I started at
age 25, I started doing both.
Making wages and making profits.
Unbelievable.
One simple philosophy changed my whole economic future.
Profits are better than wages.
I'm going to give you some.
Read all the books necessary.
Now I'm going to give
you some that started my library.
I've got one of the best.
If you saw it, you'd be impressed.
Haven't read everything in my library, but
I feel smarter just walking in it.
Okay, Gary, where are you?
Enough for the first go around here.
We'll be back this afternoon with some more.
Thank you for your patience.
Appreciate it very much.
God bless. Amen.
Ladies and gentlemen, Mr. Jim Rohn.
Wow, thank you.
Thanks, Gary.
Appreciate it.